Dave Breger Papers
Dave Breger Papers
1942-1969
Breger, David, 1908-
10.6 linear ft.
Original cartoons (1942-1969) and correspondence from readers (1942-1944).
2652417
Biographical History
David Breger (1908-1970) was an American cartoonist who coined the phrase G.I. Joe and is most famous for his World War II comic strips.
Breger was born April 15, 1908 in Chicago and began drawing cartoons in high school. Breger briefly studied architectural engineering at the University of Illinois, but graduated from Northwestern with a degree in Psychology in 1931. Breger had trouble finding employment during the Great Depression and worked in his father's sausage factory before relocating to New York City in 1937 to pursue freelance work although he had no formal art training.
Breger was drafted into the Army and created the panel cartoon Private Breger which originally started in the Saturday Evening Post in 1941. When Yank also decided to publish this comic strip, Breger chose a new title, G.I. Joe and the strips began appearing under that name in June 1942. Meanwhile King Features took over syndication of the comic strip to readers in the United States in October 1942. After Breger reached the rank of lieutenant and was discharged following the war, Private Breger became Mister Breger and a Sunday strip was added. Mister Breger ran through the end of the 1960s.
Breger was one of the earliest members of the National Cartoonists Society and wrote several books including his influential reference work How to Draw and Sell Cartoons (1966) and But That's Unprintable! (1955), a book about taboos in magazine cartoons and newspaper comics. The E.S. Bird Library at Syracuse University sponsored an exhibition of Breger's cartoons in 1979, WWII and Private Breger (Feb. 28 - April 6, 1979).
Dave Breger died January 16, 1970.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Dave Breger Papers contain original artwork for approximately 2,400 cartoons (1942-1969) and a few miscellaneous items.
Most of the original Cartoons are from Breger's syndicated comic strip Mister Breger (1946-1969), but there are also more than 370 pieces from his World War II cartoon Private Breger(1942-1945). While Private Breger features a solider dealing with his experience during wartime, Mister Breger draws on the broader human experience for its humor. Some recurring themes in the panels are weddings, jail, and Breger working as a bank teller.
The WWII era cartoons have U.S. Army press censor stamps on the back indicating the date the cartoon was reviewed and passed inspection. Also of note is the August 25, 1945 cartoon which was signed "Lt. Dave Breger" reflecting Breger's final military rank. Materials used include pen, blue pencil, watercolor, zipatone screening, bristol board and traces of pencil.
Correspondence contains mostly correspondence from readers seeking autographs and pen pal relationships; and offering their own ideas and drawings as well as from fellow soldiers and soldiers' relatives sending good wishes. The bulk of the correspondence is from 1942. There is also one item from Breger to Judith Kross - a signed and inscribed copy of one of his cartoons, donated separately from the rest of the collection.
Arrangement of the Collection
Cartoons are arranged chronologically. Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by the last name of the sender.
Related Material
See Private Breger in Britain: with an introductory discussion on Anglo-American humour between Dave Breger and Michael Barsley (Pilot Press: 1944).
has collections of over one hundred cartoonists. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Breger, David, 1908-; King Features Syndicate.; Private Breger (comic strip); Mister Breger (comic strip); Art -- Cartoonists; American wit and humor, Pictorial.; Caricatures and cartoons -- United States.; Cartoonists -- United States.; Comic books, strips, etc. -- United States.; World War, 1939-1945 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Military -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Cartoons (humorous images); Correspondence.; Photographs.; Cartoonists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Dave Breger, 1966, 1967, 1968 and 1970.
One reproduction cartoon, gift of Judith Kross, 2016.
One original cartoon (23 Oct 1962) gift of Judith Kross, 2018.
Inventory
- Private Breger, 377 items, 6/18" x 8"
  Detailed inventory available.
  - Daily cartoons, Jan 1942; Nov 1942 - Dec 1942,; Jan 1943 - Mar 1943 (Box 1)
  - Daily cartoons, Apr 1943 - Jul 1943 (Box 2)
  - Daily cartoons, Aug 1943 - Dec 1943 (Box 3)
  - Daily cartoons, Jan 1944 - Dec 1944 (Box 4)
  - Daily cartoons, 1945 (Box 5)
- Mister Breger
  - Daily cartoons, 1776 items, 8 3/4" x 10"
    - Daily cartoons, 1946; 1949,; 1951,; 1953,; 1954,; 1958,; Jan 1959 - Jun 1959 (Box 5)
    - Daily cartoons, Jul 1959 - Apr 1960 (Box 6)
    - Daily cartoons, May 1960 - Dec 1960 (Box 7)
    - Daily cartoons, Jan 1961 - Dec 1961 (Box 8)
    - Daily cartoons, Jan 1962 - Dec 1962 (Box 9)
    - Daily cartoon, 23 Oct 1962 (Box 9)
      Gift of Judith Kross, 2018.
    - Daily cartoons, Jan 1963 - Dec 1963 (Box 10)
    - Daily cartoons, Jan 1964 - Dec 1964 (Box 11)
    - Daily cartoons, 1965 (Box 12)
    - Daily cartoons, 1966; 1967,; 1969 (Box 13)
  - Sunday cartoons, 262 items, 15 3/4" x 22 1/2"
    - Sunday cartoons, 1959-1962 (Oversize 1)
    - Sunday cartoons, 1963-1964 (Oversize 2)
    - Sunday cartoons, 1965-1966 (Oversize 3)
- Correspondence
  - A-J, 1942-1944; 3 folders (Box 14)
  - Kross, Judith, 1959; photo reproduction of cartoon, signed and inscribed by Breger (Box 14)
    Gift of Judith Kross, 2016.
  - K-Z, 1942-1944; 3 folders (Box 14)
  - Unidentified, 1942 (Box 14)